Kent Iron Company Records
© 2004 University of Connecticut
Kent Iron Company Records.
1832-1882.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Kent Iron Company.
12.5 linear feet.
MSS19790009
The Kent Iron Company was formed in 1864 by a group of local residents of Kent, Connecticut. The company was established on the site of an iron foundry that is believed to have produced ammunition for Washington's army and parts of the chain that the colonists extended across the Hudson River to prevent passage of British warships. Kent Iron Company's hot blast furnace was erected on the site of the region's first blast furnace built in 1826.
History
The Housatonic River region of Connecticut, where the Kent Iron Company was located, was one of the country's most important sources of iron in the 19th century. The region contained almost all the essential resources needed in the production of iron for that time, including iron ore, lime, and hardwood for charcoal to power the blast furnaces. In 1840 there were 27 blast furnaces in operation in the area.
The Kent Iron Company was formed in 1864 by a group of local residents of Kent, Connecticut. The company was established on the site of an iron foundry that is believed to have produced ammunition for Washington's army and parts of the chain that the colonists extended across the Hudson River to prevent passage of British warships. Kent Iron Company's hot blast furnace was erected on the site of the region's first blast furnace built in 1826.
Kent Iron Company provided almost all of its own raw materials. Iron ore was extracted from the side of a mountain in a nearby town and lime was quarried in Kent. The company used teams of 10 to 12 horses or oxen to haul the resources to the furnace, while other teams hauled the finished product to the railroad. To feed the animals, the company grew its own grain on land close to the furnace, ground it at a nearby mill, and fed it to them in its own barns. Kent Iron was used extensively in the manufacture of railroad locomotives and other heavy industrial machinery. The company's daily output, about 14 tons per day, was small, but it and other foundries in the area had a profound effect on the local economy.
By the 1880s, however, the company began faltering, as did the entire local iron industry. The major reason for it decline was the increasing use of the Pennsylvania steel by manufacturing; the non-mechanized, small-scale technology of the furnaces simply could not compete with this growing large-scale industry. In addition, the region's supply of furnace iron ore and hardwood was dwindling. The company tried to adjust by changing to deep shaft mining and the use of iron ore from other areas in Connecticut and New York. And it increasingly used coal as well as charcoal to fire its furnaces to conserve the hardwood supply. All of these changes, however, raised cots and the operation was finally forced to shut down in 1892.
Scope and Content
The records of the Kent Iron Company consist of 156 volumes and include administrative, labor, production, sales and accounting records.
Arrangement
Series I: Administrative Records ( 1836-80 ) consists of notebooks, personal account books and a stock account book.
Series II: Labor Records ( 1867-1880 ) consists of two volumes of ledgers recording employee hours and work completed.
Series III: Production and Sales Records ( 1842-1882 ) contains ledgers noting the transactions of goods produced and sold. Included are ledgers detailing office and mill sales, order on account, as well as railroad shipping records.
Series IV: General Accounts ( 1832-1875 ) contains the bookkeeping records of the company and includes day books, checkbooks, cash books, ledgers of bank accounts, and mill accounting procedures.
In each series, the volumes of ledgers are arranged chronologically.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of Connecticut business records. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Iron industry and trade—Connecticut.; Connecticut—Business, industries, and trades—Iron.; Kent (Conn.)—Business, industries and trades.
Document Types:
Notebooks.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Books.
Occupations:
Iron foundry.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Custodial History
The papers of the Kent Iron Company were acquired by I.G. Davis in the 1920s, and were subsequently transferred to the University of Connecticut.
Acquisition Information
The records were in storage for some time prior to 1979 when they were transferred to the Historical Manuscripts and Archives division of the University Libraries. In 1995, Historical Manuscripts and Archives merged with Special Collections to become Archives & Special Collections, which is located in the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Administrative Records, 1836-1880
  - Stock Account Book, 1854-1870 (Volume 1)
  - Personal Account Books, 1843-1869 (Volume 2-8)
  - Notebooks, 1836-1847 (Volume 9)
  - 1870-1875 (Volume 10)
- Series II: Labor Records, 1867-1880
  - Time Books, 1874-1880 (Volume 11)
  - Work Book, 1867-1869 (Volume 12)
- Series III: Production and Sales, 1842-1882
  - Grain Account Book, 1869-1871 (Volume 13)
  - Grain Weighing Book, 1874-1872 (Volume 14)
  - Ore and Furnace Account Book, 1842-1859 (Volume 15)
  - Livery Account Books, 1861-1862 (Volume 16)
  - 1882 August - 1882 October (Volume 17)
  - Order Books, Ore Account, 1842-1874 (Volume 18-38)
  - Order Book, Lime and Ore Account, 1853-1868 (Volume 39)
  - Order Book, Lime Account, 1869-1874 (Volume 40-42)
  - Order Books, Plaster Account, 1852-1874 (Volume 43-47)
  - Order Books, Miscellaneous Accounts, 1853, 1869-1870 (Volume 48-49)
  - Invoice of Goods, 1842-1849, 1857-1863 (Volume 50-51)
  - Office Sales Books, 1875-1880 (Volume 52-55)
  - Mill Sales Books, 1875-1878 (Volume 56-57)
  - Railroad Shipping Records, 1876-1880 (Volume 58)
- Series IV: General Accounts, 1832-1875
  - Ledgers, 1838-1872 (Volume 59-66)
  - Day Books, 1840-1850 (Volume 67-77)
  - Day Books, 1844-1875 (Volume 78-133)
  - Check Books, 1868-1875 (Volume 134)
  - Cash Books, 1839-1874 (Volume 135-141)
  - Mill Account Book, 1873-1874 (Volume 142)
  - Bank Account Book, 1869-1874 (Volume 143)
  - Account Book, 1869-1871 (Volume 144)
  - Trial Balance, 1875-1878 (Volume 145)